Okay, so let's do the backward pass now.
So in the previous video, we did the
forward pass.
So now we're going to
do the backward pass,
which is calculating
late finish and late start.
The forward pass is calculating early
start, early finish.
Now we're calculating
the late finish and late
start in that order, hence
the name backward pass.
Now the starting point is always going to
be this.
our project in this example is finishing
on day 19 that's a finish date for this
project day 19 so that is our early finish
that is also going to be our late finish
that is always going to be the case right
your project has to finish in this case on
day 19 so in this case late finish and
early finish are going to be the same and
then since we're going backwards now in
order to calculate the late start,
we have to now subtract the duration.
So the late start of
any activity is always
going to be the late
finish minus the duration.
So in this case, 19 minus 3, which is 16.
Now, something I want to point out here,
and this is also a check imbalance that
you can be using as you're going through
the whole critical path exercise.
I is on the critical path.
I notice the late start and early start
are the same.
Late finish and early finish is the same.
It's on the critical path.
We have to start I on day 16 and we have
to finish on day 19.
There's no slack, no cushion.
And that is going to be the case for all
activities that are on the critical path.
Right.
So that'll be a check in balance for H,
E, D and A, they are on the critical path.
And on the critical path, all activities,
The late finish will equal the early
finish and the late start will equal the
early start.
The bottom line and
the top line will be the
same as it relates to starts and finishes.
They will not be the same on the
non-critical path activities.
B, C, F and G are not on the critical
path.
Those activities can have float.
So early start will be different to the
late start.
Early finish will be different to the late
finish on the non-critical
path activities.
So anyway, that will make more sense.
be more clearer as we go through the
exercise.
Now, let's look at I though.
I, the latest that I can start is day 16.
If I is starting on day 16,
that means the previous
activities, C, F, and H all
have to finish by day 16.
I is starting on day 16.
That means C, F, and H, the latest they
can finish is day 16.
So let's look at H.
I is starting on day 16.
that means H must have finished on day 16.
The latest it can finish is day 16.
So the late start then, the latest it can
start, 16 minus 7, which is 9.
Now, again, as that check and balance that
I mentioned here, the bottom line and top
line is the same as relates to start and
finish.
The late start is the same as the early
start.
Late finish is the same as the early
finish because it's on the critical path.
Now, let's look at F.
What's the late finish of F?
well if i has started on day 16 that means
the latest f can finish is day 16 so f and
h has to finish on day 16 so that i can
start on day 16 and then again we're just
subtracting what's a late start 16 minus
six which is 10 so let's look at this f
can either start on day 10 and it'll take
six days and it'll finish on day 15 or it
can could start on day 10 it'll take six
days and finish on day 16 right so f can
either start on day nine or it could start
on day 10 it has slack or cushion right it
can be delayed by one day no impact on the
schedule it's not on the critical path so
it has float it has uh you know it has a
slack same with c right what's the latest
that c can finish if i is starting on day
16 C has to finish on day 16.
The latest it can finish is day 16.
And 16 minus 7, what's the latest it would
have started?
16 minus 7 is 9.
So again, C could start on day 6.
It'll take 7 days, finish on day 13.
Or if it gets delayed, it could be delayed
up to 3 days and start on day 9.
It'll take 7 days and we'll finish on day
16.
As long as C, F, and
H all finish on day 16, I
can start on day 16, no
impact on the schedule.
Now, let's look at the other activities
then.
Let's look at E.
With E, you've got F and an H leading back
into E.
F and H are both dependent on E.
So as we're going backwards, F and H is
kind of like leading back into E.
F has a late start of 10.
H has a late start of 9.
So again, we have a choice.
Which one do we take?
This time, you always take the smallest
number.
In the backward pass, you always take the
smallest number when you have a choice.
In the forward pass, whenever you have a
choice, you take the highest number,
in the backward pass, you take the
smallest number, the lowest number.
So in this case, 9.
So let's look at it.
I mean, and think of
this logically, E has to
finish on day 9 so that
H can start on day 9.
If E finished on day 10, H wouldn't be
able to start on day 9.
But the other checking balance is,
it's on the critical path.
And so the late start, 9 minus 2 is 7.
Again, bottom line or bottom and top are
the same for the starts and the finishes.
Same with D then.
E starts on day 7, so D must have finished
on day 7, 7 minus 5, late start is 2.
And on the critical path.
So late start, early start is the same,
late finish, early finish are the same.
Now, let's look at B here.
Again, same principle as when we were
looking at E.
With B, you've got a C and an F leading
back into it.
C has a late start of 9.
F has a late start 10.
So again, you take the smallest number,
which is 9.
B has to finish on day 9.
So that C can start on day 9.
And then 9 minus 4, which is 5.
And now, and if you look at G then,
very simple.
H, late start is 9.
So when does G finish?
That's to finish on day 9.
G has to finish on day 9 in order for F to
start on day 9, and then 9 minus 6 is 3.
So the late start then is going to be 3.
Now, let's look at A here.
You've got both B, D and G leading back
into A.
Right, so B has a late start of 5.
D has a late start of 2.
G has a late start of 3.
So you have a choice of 3 numbers.
Again, you take the smallest number,
2.
A will finish on day two.
Again, thinking logically, A has to finish
on day two so that D can start on day two.
And then 2 minus 2, which is 0.
So again, you can see anything on the
critical path.
A, D, E, H and I, late
start and early start is the
same, late finish and
early finish are the same.
Because there is no slack, no cushion.
You have to start on that date,
you have to finish on that date.
Whereas if anything on the non-critical
path, anything not on the critical path,
the numbers are different because they
have slack, they have cushion.
Okay, that was the backward pass.